Funding for this program is provided by:
Additional
funding provided by
This is a course about Justice and we
begin with a story suppose you're the
driver of a trolley car, and your trolley
car is hurdling down the track at sixty
miles an hour and at the end of the track
you notice five workers working on the
track you tried to stop but you can't your
brakes don't work you feel desperate
because you know that if you crash into
these five workers they will all die let's
assume you know that for sure and so you
feel helpless until you notice that
there is off to the right a side track at
the end of that track
there's one worker working on track you're
steering wheel works so you
can turn the trolley car if you want to
onto this side track
killing the one but sparing the five.
Here's our first question what's the right
thing to do?
What would you do?
Let's take a poll, how many would turn the
trolley car onto the side track? How many
wouldn't?
How many would go straight ahead keep your
hands up,
those of you who'd go straight ahead.
A handful of people would, the vast
majority would turn let's hear first now
we need to begin to investigate the
reasons why you think it's the right thing
to do.
Let's begin with those in the majority,
who would turn to go onto side track?
Why would you do it, what would be your
reason?
Who's willing to volunteer a reason? Go
ahead, stand up.
Because it can't be right to kill five
people when you can only kill one person
instead.
it wouldn't be right to kill five if you
could kill one person
instead that's a good reason that's a good
reason
who else? does everybody agree with that
reason?
go ahead.
Well I was thinking it was the same reason
it was on 9/11 we regard the people who
flew the plane who flew the plane into the
Pennsylvania field as heroes because they
chose to kill the people on the plane and
not kill more people in big buildings.
So the principle there was the same on
9/11 it's tragic circumstance, but better
to kill one so that five can live is that
the reason most of you have, those of you
who would turn, yes?
Let's hear now from those in the minority
those who
wouldn't turn.
Well I think that same type of mentality
that justifies genocide and
totalitarianism in order to save one type
of race you wipe out the other.
so what would you do in this case?
You would to avoid the horrors of genocide
you would
crash into the five and kill them?
Presumably yes. okay who else?
That's a brave answer, thank you.
Let's consider another trolley car case
and
see whether those of you in the majority
want to adhere to the principle, better
that one should die so that five should
live.
This time you're not the driver of the
trolley car, you're an onlooker standing
on a bridge overlooking a trolley car
track and down the track comes a trolley
car at the end of the track are five
workers the brakes don't work the
trolley car is about to careen into the
five and kill them and now you're not the
driver you really feel helpless until you
notice standing
next to you leaning over the bridge is
it very fat man.
And you could give him a shove he would
fall over
the bridge onto the track right in the way
of the
trolley car he would die but he would
spare
the five.
Now, how many would push the fat man over
the bridge?
Raise your hand. How many wouldn't?
Most people wouldn't.
Here's the obvious question, what became
of the principle better to save
five lives even if it means sacrificing
one, what became of the principal that
almost everyone endorsed in the first case
I need to hear from someone who was in the
majority in both cases is how do you
explain the difference between the two?
The second one I guess involves an active
choice of pushing a person and down which
I guess that that person himself would
otherwise not have been involved in the
situation at all and so to choose on his
behalf I guess
to involve him in something that he
otherwise would have this escaped is I
guess more than what you have in the first
case where the three parties, the driver
and the two sets of workers are already I
guess in this situation.
but the guy working, the one on the track
off to the side he didn't choose to
sacrifice his life any more than the fat
guy did, did he?
That's true, but he was on the tracks.
this guy was on the bridge.
Go ahead, you can come back if you want.
Alright, it's a hard question but you did
well you did very well it's a hard
question.
who else can find a way of reconciling the
reaction of the majority in these two
cases? Yes?
Well I guess in the first case where you
have the one worker and the five it's a
choice between those two, and you have to
make a certain choice and people are going
to die because of the trolley car not
necessarily because of your direct
actions.
The trolley car is a runway, thing and you
need to make in a split second choice
whereas pushing the fat man over is an
actual act of murder on your part you have
control over that whereas you may not have
control over the trolley car.
So I think that it's a slightly different
situation. Alright who has a reply?
Is that, who has a reply to that?
no that was good, who has a way who wants
to reply? Is that a way out of this?
I don't think that's a very good reason
because you choose either way you have to
choose who dies because you either choose
to turn and kill a person which is an act
of conscious thought to turn, or you
choose to push the fat man over which is
also an active conscious action so either
way you're making a choice.
Do you want to reply?
Well I'm not really sure that that's the
case, it just still seems kind of
different, the act of actually pushing
someone over onto the tracks and killing
them, you are actually killing him
yourself, you're pushing him with your own
hands you're pushing and that's different
than steering something that is going to
cause death into another...you know it
doesn't really sound right saying it now
when I'm up here. No that's good, what's
your name? Andrew.
Andrew and let me ask you this question
Andrew, suppose
standing on the bridge next to the fat man
I didn't have to push him, suppose he was
standing over a trap door that I could
open by turning a steering wheel
like that would you turn it?
For some reason that still just seems more
more wrong.
I mean maybe if you just accidentally like
leaned into this steering wheel or
something like that or but, or say that
the car is hurdling towards a switch that
will drop the trap then I could agree with
that.
Fair enough, it still seems wrong in a way
that it doesn't seem wrong in the first
case to turn, you say An in another way, I
mean in the first situation you're
involved directly with the situation in
the second one you're an onlooker as well.
So you have the choice of becoming
involved or not by pushing the fat man.
Let's forget for the moment about this
case, that's good, but let's imagine a
different case.
This time your doctor in an emergency room
and six patients come
to you they've been in a terrible trolley
car wreck five of them sustained moderate
injuries one is severely injured you could
spend all day caring for the one severely
injured victim, but in that time the five
would die, or you could look after the
five, restore them to health, but during
that time the one severely injured person
would die.
How many would save the five now as the
doctor?
How many would save the one?
Very few people, just a handful of people.
Same reason I assume, one life versus
five.
Now consider another doctor case this time
you're a transplant surgeon and
you have five patients each in desperate
need of an organ transplant in order to
survive on needs a heart one a lung, one a
kidney, one a liver and
the fifth a pancreas.
And you have no organ donors you are about
to see you them
die and then it occurs to you that in the
next room there's a healthy guy
who came in for a checkup.
and he is you like
that and he's taking a nap
you could go in very quietly yank out the
five organs, that person
would die but you can save the five.
How many would do it? Anyone?
How many? Put your hands up if you would
do it.
Anyone in the balcony? You would?
Be careful don't lean over too much How
many wouldn't?
All right.
What do you say, speak up in the balcony,
you who would yank out the organs, why?
I'd actually like to explore slightly
alternate possibility of just taking the
one of the five he needs an organ who dies
first and using their four
healthy organs to save the other four
That's a pretty
good idea.
That's a great idea except for the fact
that you
just wrecked the philosophical point.
Let's step back from these stories and
these arguments to notice a couple of
things about the way the arguments have
began to unfold.
Certain moral principles have already
begun to emerge from the
discussions we've had and let's consider
what those moral principles look
like the first moral principle that
emerged from the discussion said that the
right thing to do the moral thing to do
depends on the consequences that will
result from your action at the end of the
day better that five should live
even if one must die.
That's an example of consequentialist
moral
reasoning.
consequentialist moral reasoning locates
morality in the consequences of an act.
In the state of the world that will result
from the thing you do but then we went a
little further, we considered those other
cases and people weren't so sure
about consequentialist moral reasoning
when people
hesitated to push the fat man over the
bridge or to yank out the organs of the
innocent patient people gestured towards
reasons having
to do with the intrinsic quality of the
act itself.
Consequences be what they may.
People were reluctant people thought it
was just wrong categorically wrong
to kill a person an innocent person even
for the sake of saving five
lives, at least these people thought that
in the second version of each
story we reconsidered so this points a
second categorical way of thinking
about moral reasoning categorical moral
reasoning locates morality in certain
absolute moral requirements in certain
categorical duties and rights regardless
of the consequences.
We're going to explore in the days and
weeks to come the contrast between
consequentialist and categorical moral
principles.
The most influential example of
consequential moral reasoning is
utilitarianism, a doctrine invented by
Jeremy Bentham, the eighteenth century
English political philosopher.
The most important philosopher of
categorical moral reasoning is
the eighteenth century German philosopher
Emmanuel Kant.
So we will look at those two different
modes of moral reasoning assess them and
also consider others.
If you look at the syllabus, you'll notice
that we read a number of great and famous
books.
Books by Aristotle John Locke Emanuel
Kant, John Stuart Mill, and
others.
You'll notice too from the syllabus that
we don't only read these books, we also
all take up contemporary political and
legal controversies that raise
philosophical questions.
We will debate equality and inequality,
affirmative action, free speech versus
hate speech, same sex marriage, military
conscription, a range of practical
questions, why not just to enliven these
abstract and distant books but to make
clear to bring out what's at stake in our
everyday lives including our political
lives, for philosophy.
So we will read these books and we will
debate these issues and we'll see how each
informs and illuminates the other.
This may sound appealing enough but here I
have to issue a
warning, and the warning is this to read
these
books in this way, as an exercise in
self-knowledge, to
read them in this way carry certain risks
risks that are both personal and
political, risks that every student of
political philosophy have known.
These risks spring from that fact that
philosophy teaches us and
unsettles us by confronting us with what
we already know.
There's an irony the difficulty of this
course consists in the fact that it
teaches what you already know.
It works by taking what we know from
familiar unquestioned settings,
and making it strange.
That's how those examples worked worked
the hypotheticals with which we began with
their mix of playfulness and sobriety.
it's also how these philosophical books
work.
Philosophy estranges us from the familiar
not by supplying new
information but by inviting and provoking
a new way of
seeing but, and here's the risk, once the
familiar
turns strange, it's never quite the same
again.
Self-knowledge is like lost innocence,
however unsettling you
find it, it can never be unthought or
unknown what makes this enterprise
difficult
but also riveting, is that moral and
political philosophy
is a story and you don't know where this
story will lead but what you do know is
that the story is about you.
Those are the personal risks, now what of
the political risks.
one way of introducing of course like this
would be to promise you that by reading
these books and debating these issues you
will become a better more responsible
citizen.
You will examine the presuppositions of
public policy, you will hone your
political judgment you'll become a more
effective participant in public affairs
but this would be a partial and misleading
promise political philosophy for the most
part hasn't worked that way.
You have to allow for the possibility that
political philosophy may make you a worse
citizen rather than a better one or at
least a worse citizen before it makes
you a better one and that's because
philosophy is a
distancing even debilitating activity And
you see this
going back to Socrates there's a dialogue,
the Gorgias in which one of Socrates’
friends Calicles tries to talk him out of
philosophizing.
calicles tells Socrates philosophy is a
pretty toy if one indulges in it with
moderation at the right time of life but
if one pursues it further than one should
it is absolute ruin.
Take my advice calicles says, abandon
argument learn the accomplishments of
active life, take for your models not
those people who spend their time on these
petty quibbles, but those who have a good
livelihood and reputation and many other
blessings.
So Calicles is really saying to Socrates
quit philosophizing,
get real go to business school and
calicles did have a point he had a point
because philosophy distances us from
conventions from established assumptions
and from settled beliefs.
those are the risks, personal and
political and in the face of these risks
there is a characteristic evasion, the
name of the evasion is skepticism.
It's the idea well it goes something like
this we didn't resolve, once and for
all, either the cases or the principles we
were arguing when we began
and if Aristotle and Locke and Kant and
Mill haven't solved these questions after
all of these years who are we to think
that we here in Sanders Theatre over the
course a semester can resolve them and so
maybe it's just a matter of
each person having his or her own
principles and there's nothing more to be
said about it no way of reasoning that's
the evasion.
The evasion of skepticism to which I would
offer the following reply: it's true these
questions have been debated for a very
long time but the very fact that they have
reoccurred and persisted may suggest that
though they're impossible in one sense
their unavoidable in another and the
reason they're unavoidable the reason
they're inescapable is that we live some
answer to these questions every day.
So skepticism, just throwing up their
hands and giving up on moral reflection,
is no solution Emanuel Kant described very
well the problem with skepticism
when he wrote skepticism is a resting
place for human reason where it can
reflect upon its dogmatic wanderings but
it is no dwelling place for permanent
settlement.
Simply to acquiesce in skepticism, Kant
wrote, can never suffice to overcome
the restless of reason.
I've tried to suggest through theses
stories and these arguments some sense of
the risks and temptations of the perils
and the possibilities I would simply
conclude by saying that the aim of this
course is to awaken the
restlessness of reason and to see where it
might lead thank
you very much.
Like, in a situation that desperate, you
have to do what you have to do to survive.
You have to do what you have to do you?
You've gotta do What you gotta do.
pretty much, If you've been going nineteen
days without any food someone has to take
the sacrifice, someone has to make the
sacrifice and people can survive.
Alright that's good, what's your name?
Marcus.
Marcus, what do you say to Marcus?
Last time we started out last time
with some stores with some moral dilemmas
about trolley cars and about
doctors and healthy patients vulnerable to
being victims of organ
transplantation we noticed two things
about the arguments we
had one had to do with the way we were
arguing it began with our judgments in
particular cases we tried to articulate
the reasons or the principles lying
behind our judgments and then confronted
with a new case we
found ourselves re-examining those
principles revising each in the
light of the other and we noticed the
built-in pressure to try to bring into
alignment our judgments about particular
cases and the principles we would endorse
on reflection we also noticed something
about the substance of the arguments
that emerged from the discussion.
We noticed that sometimes we were tempted
to locate the morality of an act in the
consequences in the results, in the state
of the world that it brought about.
We called is consequentialist moral
reason.
But we also noticed that in some cases we
weren't swayed only
by the results sometimes, many of us felt,
that not just consequences but also the
intrinsic quality or character of the act
matters morally.
Some people argued that there are certain
things that are just categorically wrong
even if they bring about a good result
even if they save five people at the
cost of one life.
So we contrasted consequentialist moral
principles with
categorical ones.
Today and in the next few days we will
begin to examine one of the
most influential versions of
consequentialist moral theory and
that's the philosophy of utilitarianism.
Jeremy Bentham, the eighteenth century
English political philosopher gave first
the first clear systematic expression to
the utilitarian
moral theory.
And Bentham's idea, his essential idea is
a very simple one with a lot of
morally intuitive appeal.
Bentham's idea is the following the right
thing to do the
just thing to do it's to maximize
utility. What did he mean by utility?
He meant by utility the balance of
pleasure
over pain, happiness over suffering.
Here's how we arrived at the principle of
maximizing utility.
He started out by observing that all of us
all human beings are governed by
two sovereign masters, pain and pleasure.
We human beings like pleasure and dislike
pain and so we should base morality
whether we are thinking of what to do in
our own lives or whether as legislators or
citizens we are thinking about what
the law should be, the right thing to do
individually or collectively
is to maximize, act in a way that
maximizes the overall level of
happiness.
Bentham's utilitarianism is sometimes
summed up with the slogan the greatest
good for the greatest number.
With this basic principle of utility on
hand, let's begin to test it and to
examine it by turning to another case
another story but this time not a
hypothetical story, a real-life story the
case of the Queen versus Dudley and
Stephens.
This was a nineteenth-century British law
case that's famous and much
debated in law schools.
Here's what happened in the case I'll
summarize the story and then I want to
hear how you would rule imagining that
you are the jury.
A newspaper account of the time described
the background: A sadder story of disaster
at sea was never told than that of the
survivors of the yacht Mignonette.
The ship foundered in the south Atlantic
thirteen hundred miles from the cape there
were four in the crew, Dudley was the
captain Stephens was the first mate Brooks
was a sailor, all men of excellent
character, or so the newspaper account
tells us.
The fourth crew member was the cabin boy,
Richard Parker seventeen years
old.
He was an orphan he had no family and he
was on his first
long voyage at sea.
He went, the news account tells us, rather
against the advice of his friends.
He went in the hopefulness of youthful
ambition thinking the journey would make a
man of him.
Sadly it was not to be, the facts of the
case were not in dispute, a wave hit the
ship and the Mignonette went down.
The four crew members escaped to a
lifeboat the only food they had
were two cans of preserved turnips no
fresh water for the first three
days they ate nothing on the fourth day
that opened one of the cans of turnips and
ate it.
The next day they caught a turtle together
with the other can of turnips the turtle
enabled them to subsist for the next few
days and then for eight days they had
nothing no food no water.
Imagine yourself in a situation like that
what would you do?
Here's what they did by now the cabin boy
Parker is lying at the bottom of the
lifeboat in a corner because he had drunk
sea water against the advice of the others
and he had become ill and he appeared to
be dying so on the nineteenth day
Dudley, the captain, suggested that they
should all have a lottery.
That they should all draw lots to see who
would die to save the rest.
Brooks refused he didn't like the lottery
idea we don't know whether this was
because he didn't want to take that chance
or because he believed in categorical
moral principles but in any case no lots
were drawn.
The next day there was still no ship in
sight so a Dudley told Brooks to avert his
gaze and he motioned to Stephens that the
boy Parker had better be killed.
Dudley offered a prayer he told a the boy
his time had come and he killed him with a
pen knife stabbing him in the jugular
vein.
Brooks emerged from his conscientious
objection to share in the gruesome bounty.
For four days the three of them fed on the
body and blood of the cabin boy.
True story. And then they were rescued.
Dudley describes their rescue in his diary
with staggering
euphemism, quote: "on the twenty fourth
day as we were having
our breakfast a ship appeared at last."
The three survivors were picked up by a
German ship.
They were taken back to Falmouth in
England where they were arrested and tried
Brooks turned state's witness Dudley and
Stephens went to trial.
They didn't dispute the facts they claimed
they had acted out of necessity that was
their defense they argued in effect better
that one should die so that three could
survive the prosecutor wasn't swayed by
that argument he said murder is murder
and so the case went to trial.
Now imagine you are the jury and just to
simplify the discussion put aside the
question of law, and let's assume that you
as the jury are charged with
deciding whether what they did was morally
permissible or not.
How many would vote not guilty,
that what they did was morally
permissible?
And how many would vote guilty what they
did was morally wrong?
A pretty sizable majority.
Now let's see what people's reasons are,
and let me begin with those who are in the
minority. Let's hear first from the
defense of Dudley and Stephens.
Why would you morally exonerate them?
What are your reasons?
I think it's I think it is morally
reprehensible but I think that there's a
distinction between what's morally
reprehensible what makes someone legally
accountable in other words the night as
the judge said what's always moral isn't
necessarily against the law and while I
don't think that necessity justifies theft
or murder any illegal act, at some point
your degree of necessity does in fact
exonerate you form any guilt. ok.
other defenders, other voices for the
defense?
Moral justifications for what they did?
yes, thank you I just feel like in a
situation that desperate you have to do
what you have to do to survive.
You have to do what you have to do ya, you
gotta do what you gotta do, pretty much.
If you've been going nineteen days without
any food you know someone just has to take
the sacrifice has to make sacrifices and
people can survive and furthermore from
that let's say they survived and then they
become productive members of society who
go home and then start like a million
charity organizations and this and that
and this and that, I mean they benefit
everybody in the end so I mean I don't
know what they did afterwards, I mean they
might have gone on and killed more people
but whatever. what? what if they were
going home and turned out to be assassins?
What if they were going home and turned
out to be assassins?
You would want to know who they
assassinated.
That's true too, that's fair I would wanna
know who they assassinated.
alright that's good, what's your name?
Marcus.
We've heard a defense a couple voices for
the defense now we need to hear from the
prosecution most people think what they
did was
wrong, why?
One of the first things that I was
thinking was, oh well if they haven't been
eating for a really long time, maybe then
they're mentally affected that
could be used for the defense, a possible
argument that oh, that they weren't in a
proper state of mind, they were making
decisions that they otherwise wouldn't be
making, and if that's an appealing
argument that you have to be in an altered
mindset to do something like that it
suggests that people who find that
argument convincing do you think that
they're acting immorally.
But I want to know what you think you're
defending you k 0:37:41.249,0:37:45.549
you voted to convict right?
yeah I don't think that they acted in
morally appropriate way. And why not?
What do you say, Here's Marcus he just
defended them, he said, you heard what he
said, yes I did yes that you've got to do
what you've got to do in a case like that.
What do you say to Marcus?
They didn't, that there is no situation
that would allow
human beings to take the idea of fate or
the other people's lives into their own
hands that we don't have that kind of
power.
Good, okay thanks you, and what's your
name? Britt? okay. who else?
What do you say?
Stand up I'm wondering if Dudley and
Stephens had asked for Richard Parker's
consent in, you know, dying, if that would
would that
exonerate them from an act of murder, and
if so is that still morally justifiable?
That's interesting, alright consent, now
hang on, what's your name? Kathleen.
Kathleen says suppose so what would that
scenario look like?
so in the story Dudley is there, pen knife
in hand, but instead of the prayer or
before the prayer, he says, Parker, would
you mind we're desperately hungry, as
Marcus
empathizes with we're desperately hungry
you're not going to last long anyhow, you
can be a martyr, would you be a martyr how
about it
Parker?
Then, then then what do you think, would
be morally
justified then?
Suppose Parker in his semi-stupor says
okay I don't think it'll be
morally justifiable but I'm wondering.
Even then, even then it wouldn't be?
No You don't think that even with consent
it would be morally justified.
Are there people who think who want to
take up Kathleen's consent idea and who
think that that would make it morally
justified?
Raise your hand if it would if you think
it would.
That's very interesting Why would consent
make a moral
difference? Why would it?
Well I just think that if he was making
his own original idea and it was his idea
to start with then that would be the only
situation in which I would see it being
appropriate in anyway
0:40:25.940,0:40:28.359 because that way
you couldn't make the argument that he was
pressured you know it’s three to one or
whatever the ratio was, and I think that
if he was making a decision to give his
life then he took on the agency to
sacrifice himself which some people might
see as admirable and other people might
disagree with that decision.
So if he came up with the idea that's the
only kind of consent we could have
confidence in morally, then it would be
okay otherwise it would be kind of
coerced consent under the circumstances
you think.
Is there anyone who thinks that the even
the consent of Parker would
not justify their killing him? Who thinks
that?
Yes, tell us why, stand up I think that
Parker would be killed with the hope that
the other crew members would be rescued so
there's no definite reason that he should
be killed because you don't know when
they're going to get rescued so if you
kill him you're killing him in vain do you
keep killing a crew member until you're
rescued and then you're left with no one?
because someone's going to die eventually?
Well the moral logic of the situation
seems to be that.
That they would keep on picking off the
weakest maybe, one by one, until
they were rescued and in this case luckily
when three at least were still alive.
Now if if Parker did give his consent
would it be all right do you think or not?
No, it still wouldn't be right. Tell us
why wouldn't be all right.
First of all, cannibalism, I believe is
morally incorrect so you shouldn’t be
eating a human anyway.
So cannibalism is morally objectionable
outside so then even in the
scenario of waiting until someone died
still it would be objectionable.
Yes, to me personally I feel like of it
all depends on one's personal morals, like
we can't just, like this is just my
opinion of course other people are going
to disagree.
Well let's see, let's hear what their
disagreements are and then we'll see if
they have reasons that can persuade you or
not.
Let's try that Let's now is there
someone who can explain, those of you who
are tempted by consent can you
explain why consent makes such a moral
difference, what about the lottery idea
does that count as consent.
Remember at the beginning Dudley proposed
a lottery suppose that they had agreed
to a lottery then how many would then say
it was all right.
Say there was a lottery, cabin boy lost,
and the rest of the story unfolded.
How many people would say it's morally
permissible?
So the numbers are rising if we add a
lottery, let's hear from one of you for
whom the lottery would make a moral
difference why would it?
I think the essential element, in my mind
that makes it a crime is the idea that
they decided at some point that their
lives were more important than his, and
that I mean that's kind of the basis for
really any crime right?
It's like my needs, my desire is a more
important than yours and mine take
precedent and if they had done a lottery
were everyone consented that someone
should die and it's sort of like they're
all sacrificing themselves, to save the
rest, Then it would be all right?
A little grotesque but, But morally
permissible? Yes.
what's your name? Matt.
so, Matt for you what bothers you is not
the cannibalism, but the
lack of due process.
I guess you could say that And can someone
who agrees with Matt
say a little bit more about why a lottery
would make
it, in your view, morally permissible.
The way I understood it originally was
that that was the whole issue is that the
cabin boy was never consulted about
whether or not it something was going to
happen to him even though with the
original lottery whether or not he would
be a part of that it was just decided that
he was the one that was going to die.
Yes that's what happened in the actual
case but if there were a lottery and they
all agreed to the procedure you think that
would be okay?
Right, because everyone knows that there's
gonna be a death whereas you know the
cabin boy didn't know that this discussion
was even happening there was no you know
forewarning for him to know that hey, I
may be the one that's dying.
Okay, now suppose the everyone agrees to
the lottery they have the lottery the
cabin boy loses any changes his mind.
You've already decided, it's like a verbal
contract, you can't go back on that.
You've decided the decision was made you
know if you know you're dying for the
reason for at others to live, you would,
you know if the someone else had died you
know that you would consume them, so But
then he could say I
know, but I lost.
I just think that that's the whole moral
issue is that there was no consulting of
the cabin boy and that that's what makes
it the most horrible is that he had no
idea what was even going on, that if he
had known what was going on it would be a
bit more understandable.
Alright, good, now I want to hear so
there's some who think it's morally
permissible but only about twenty percent,
led
by Marcus, then there are some who say the
real problem here is the lack
of consent whether the lack of consent to
a lottery to a fair procedure
or Kathleen's idea, lack of consent at the
moment of
death and if we add consent then more
people are
willing to consider the sacrifice morally
justified.
I want to hear now finally from those of
you who think even with consent even with
a lottery even with a final murmur of
consent from Parker at the
very last moment it would still be wrong
and why would it be wrong that's
what I want to hear.
well the whole time I've been leaning
towards the categorical moral reasoning
and I think that there's a possibility I'd
be okay with the idea of the lottery and
then loser taking into their own hands to
kill themselves so there wouldn't be an
act of murder but I still think that even
that way it's coerced and also I don't
think that there's any remorse like in
Dudley's diary we're getting our breakfast
it seems as though he's just sort of like,
oh, you know that whole idea of not
valuing someone else's life so that makes
me feel like I have to take the
categorical stance. You want to throw the
book at him.
when he lacks remorse or a sense of having
done anything wrong. Right.
Alright, good so are there any other
defenders who who say
it's just categorically wrong, with or
without consent, yes stand up. Why?
I think undoubtedly the way our society is
shaped, murder is murder murder is murder
and every way our society looks down at it
in the same light and I don't think it's
any different in any case.
Good now let me ask you a question, there
were three lives at stake versus one,
the one, that the cabin boy, he had no
family he had no dependents, these other
three had families back home in England
they had dependents they had wives and
children think back to Bentham, Bentham
says we have to consider the welfare, the
utility, the happiness of everybody.
We have to add it all up so it's not just
numbers three against one it's also all
of those people at home in fact the London
newspaper at the time and popular opinion
sympathized with them Dudley in Stephens
and the paper said if they weren't
motivated by affection and concern for
their loved ones at home and dependents,
surely they wouldn't have done this.
Yeah, and how is that any different from
people on the corner trying to having the
same desire to feed their family, I don't
think it's any different.
I think in any case if I'm murdering you
to advance my status, that's murder and I
think that we should look at all of that
in the same light.
Instead of criminalizing certain
activities and making certain things seem
more violent and savage when in that same
case it's all the same act and mentality
that goes into the murder, a necessity to
feed their families.
Suppose there weren't three, supposed
there were thirty, three hundred, one life
to save three hundred or in more time,
three thousand or suppose the stakes were
even bigger. Suppose the stakes were even
bigger I think it's still the same deal.
Do you think Bentham was wrong to say the
right thing to do is to add up the
collected happiness, you think he's wrong
about that?
I don't think he is wrong, but I think
murder is murder in any case.
Well then Bentham has to be wrong if
you're right he's wrong.
okay then he's wrong. Alright thank you,
well done.
Alright, let's step back from this
discussion and notice
how many objections have we heard to what
they did.
we heard some defenses of what they did
the defense has had to do with necessity
the dire circumstance and, implicitly at
least, the idea that numbers
matter and not only numbers matter but the
wider effects matter their families back
home, their dependents Parker was an
orphan, no one would miss him.
so if you add up if you tried to calculate
the balance of
happiness and suffering you might have a
case for saying what they did was
the right thing then we heard at least
three different types of
objections, we heard an objection that's
said what they did was categorically
wrong, right here at the end categorically
wrong.
Murder is murder it's always wrong even if
it increases the overall happiness of
society the categorical objection.
But we still need to investigate why
murder is categorically wrong.
Is it because even cabin boys have certain
fundamental rights?
And if that's the reason where do those
rights come from if not from some idea of
the larger welfare or utility or
happiness? Question number one.
Others said a lottery would make a
difference a fair procedure,
Matt said.
And some people were swayed by that.
That's not a categorical objection exactly
it's saying everybody has to be
counted as an equal even though, at the
end of the day one can be sacrificed for
the general welfare.
That leaves us with another question to
investigate, Why does agreement to certain
procedure, even a fair procedure, justify
whatever result flows from the
operation of that procedure? Question
number two.
and question number three the basic idea
of consent.
Kathleen got us on to this.
If the cabin boy had agreed himself and
not under duress as
was added then it would be all right to
take his life to save the rest.
Even more people signed on to that idea
but that raises a third philosophical
question what is the moral work that
consent does?
Why does an act of consent make such a
moral difference that an act that would be
wrong, taking a life, without consent is
morally permissible with
consent?
To investigate those three questions we're
going to have to read some philosophers
and starting next time we're going to read
Bentham, and John Stuart Mill,
utilitarian philosophers.
Don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of Justice join the
conversation, take a pop quiz, watch
lectures you've
missed, and a lot more. Visit
www.justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.
Funding for the program is provided by
Additional funding provided by